What if my skin dermatitis worsens?
Part Two: Silver Cream and Mepilex Padding
90% of patients get through the first step of
skin care management
and don't have further damage.
But for about 10 to 15% of our patients,
they will experience a higher grade of
radiation dermatitis.
Patients with this degree of skin dermatitis experience
moist desquamation or opening of the skin.
These using breaks in the skin pose two issues:
1) greater pain and 2) a higher risk for infection.
To treat this higher grade skin damage,
we use astronger cream, Silver Sulfadiazene
or Silvadene.
This cream offers greater protection to the skin
and an antibiotic component to prevent infection.
To use this silver cream, apply it twice a day,
once in the morning and once at night
to all the areas of the skin
that are now open and oozing.
You have the option to use this
silver cream with this spot method:
only covering up the open areas of skin
in conjunction with moisturizer,
which is still applied
to all other areas of the head and neck.
Or you can simply apply the silver cream,
like moisturizer, everywhere on the head and neck.
This silver cream is not over-the-counter
and is available only via prescription.
Please check in with your doctor
and their team for a script.
Samples are also available.
In addition to the silver cream,
we have padding to further protect those
areas of greater skin damage,
high friction and or higher sensitivity to touch,
such as the skin near the shirt collar,
backpack straps, etc.
This padding is administered after
applying the silver cream
and can be cut to fit hard to reach areas.
Like a band aid,
Mepilex padding has adhesive edges
with a soft center
and come in a variety of different sizes.
We will provide you with these Mepilex Paddings.
Please do not place the adhesive
edges over open oozing areas.
A note on dress:
To further reduce discomfort,
we ask if you can wear low
neck shirts that decrease the potential
for friction rubs.
Of course,
this is not always possible due to dress
requirements for work and daily life.